Guide to the Chauncey McKinley Louttit Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Chauncey McKinley Louttit papers
1917-1956
MS 333
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.5
The papers consist of correspondence and professional papers concerning Chauncey Louttit's teaching and administrative duties, his tour in the Navy during World War II, his publication activities, and his duties as editor of Psychological Abstracts. The papers cover his years at Indiana University, 1931-1940; the controversy with president Asa S. Knowles while he was dean of Sampson College, 1946-1947; his deanship at the Colesburg undergraduate division of the University of Illinois; and his chairmanship of the psychology department at Wayne State University.
Louttit, C. M. (Chauncey McKinley), 1901-1956
Existence and Location of Copies
Additional information not yet available in the online version of the finding aid exists in the repository. Contact Manuscripts and Archives for assistance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were given to Yale University Library by Richard T. Louttit in 1959.
Arrangement
Boxes 1-10 are arranged alphabetically, mainly by correspondent, but in some cases by subject. Boxes 11-26 are arranged chronologically, with some materials in bound, numbered volumes.
Scope and Contents
The Chauncey McKinley Louttit Papers consist of 10.5 linear feet of correspondence and other materials (such as meetings and organizational reports, invoices, and programs) spanning from 1917 to 1956. They concern Louttit's teaching and administrative duties, his tour in the U.S. Navy during World War II, his controversy with President Asa Knowles while he was Dean of Faculty at Sampson College, and various matters connected with his deanship at the University of Illinois and his chairing of the psychology department at Wayne State University.
Biographical / Historical
Chauncey McKinley Louttit was born in Buffalo, New York, on October 9, 1901. He graduated from Hobart College in 1925 and received his Ph.D. from Yale in 1928. A pioneer in the teaching of psychology, during his long career he was associated variously with the University of Indiana, Ohio State University, Sampson College, the University of Illinois (Galesburg and Urbana), and Wayne State University. The author of several texts and innumerable articles and reviews, Louttit was also the editor and guiding spirit of Psychological Abstracts, a member of many professional groups, and a governmental and industrial consultant on various aspects of human behavior. He died on May 24, 1956.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Education; Naval education -- United States; Psychologists -- Correspondence; Psychology; Educators; Psychologists; Bingham, Harold C. (Harold Clyde), 1888-1964; Boring, Edwin Garrigues, 1886-1968; Carmichael, Leonard, 1898-1973; Cattell, James McKeen, 1860-1944; Conklin, Edmund S., 1884-1942; Dashiell, John Frederick, 1888-1975; Dodge, Raymond, 1871-1942; Doll, Edgar A. (Edgar Arnold), 1889-; Holstead, Ward Campbell, 1908-; Hunter, Walter S. (Walter Samuel), 1889-1954; Knowles, Asa S. (Asa Smallidge), 1909-; Louttit, C. M. (Chauncey McKinley), 1901-1956; McDougall, William, 1871-1938; Murchison, Carl, 1887-1961; Porteus, S. D. (Stanley David), 1883-1972; Prince, Morton, 1854-1929; Stone, Calvin P. (Calvin Perry), 1892-1954; Tolman, Edward Chace, 1886-1959; Watson, John B. (John Broadus), 1878-1958; Yerkes, Robert M. (Robert Mearns), 1876-1956; American Psychological Association; Sampson College; University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign campus); Wayne State University. Department of Psychology
- Alphabetical Files
  - A -APA, Committee (Box 1)
  - APA, Council -APA, Editorial council (1952) (Box 2)
  - APA, Editorial council (1953) -Bulchholz, H. E. (Box 3)
  - Bucklew, John -Cornehlson, John H. (Box 4)
  - Costin, Frank -F (misc.) (Box 5)
  - Fryer, D.H. - Hordines, John (Box 6)
  - Hunt, William A. - Marquis, A.N., & Co. (Box 7)
  - Mental hygiene - Psychological Abstracts (Box 8)
  - Psychological Abstracts, Advisory Committee - Shartle, C.L. (Box 9)
  - Smith, Bruce Lannes - Z (Box 10)
- Chronological Files
  - 1927-1940 (Box 11)
  - 1941-1943 (Box 12)
  - 1944 (Box 13)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 14)
  - 1946-1954 (Box 15)
  - Volume I, 1917-1929 (Box 16)
  - Volume II, 1930 (Box 16)
  - Volume III, 1931 (Box 16)
  - Volume IV, 1932 (Box 16)
  - Volume V, 1933 (Box 17)
  - Volume VI, 1934 (Box 17)
  - Volume VII, 1935 (Box 18)
  - Volume VIII, 1936 (Box 18)
  - Volume IX, 1936-1940 (Box 19)
  - Volume X, 1936-1940 (Box 19)
  - Volume XI, 1937 (Box 20)
  - Volume XII, 1937-1945 (Box 21)
  - Volume XIII, 1938 (Box 22)
  - Volume XIV, 1939 (Box 23)
  - Volume XV, 1940 (Box 24)
  - Volume XVI, 1941 (Box 25)
  - Volume XVII, 1941 (Box 25)
  - Unnumbered volumes, 1942-1943 (Box 26)